Guide to the Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize Photography Collection, 1996-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize Photography collection 1996-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies.
8.0 Linear Feet 38 Items
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor documentary prize is awarded by Duke University's Center for Documentary Studies to a writer and a photographer in the early stages of a documentary project. The prize was created to encourage collaboration between documentary writers and photographers in the tradition of the acclaimed photographer Dorothea Lange and writer and social scientist Paul Taylor.
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize Photography Collection, 1996-2005, houses the work of five documentary photographers - Mary Berridge, Rob Amberg, Jason Eskenazi, Jim Lommasson, and Dona Ann McAdams - consisting of 38 color and black-and-white prints created as part of documentary projects that were awarded the Lange-Taylor Prize. Topics includes boxing gyms; the effects of highway construction in the Appalachian mountains; HIV-positive women; the transition between traditional and modern life in mountain villages in the Causcasus; and living with schizophrenia, with images taken around Coney Island. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research but restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize Photography Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007 and 2011.
Historical Note
The year 2010 marked the twentieth anniversary of the Dorothea Lange–Paul Taylor documentary prize, an award given by the Center for Documentary Studies. First announced a year after the Center's founding at Duke University, the prize was created to encourage collaboration between documentary writers and photographers in the tradition of the acclaimed photographer Dorothea Lange and writer and social scientist Paul Taylor. In 1941 Lange and Taylor published An American Exodus, a book that renders human experience eloquently in text and images and remains a seminal work in documentary studies. The Lange-Taylor Prize honors their important collaborative work.
The Lange-Taylor Prize is offered to a writer and a photographer in the early stages of a documentary project. By encouraging such collaborative efforts, the Center for Documentary Studies supports the documentary process in which writers and photographers work together to record the human story.
[Overview from the CDS website, August 2010.]
Collection Overview
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize Photography Collection consists of 38 photographic prints created by five photographers, all winners of the Center for Documentary Studies' Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize. Topics includes boxing gyms; the effects of highway construction in the Appalachian mountains; HIV-positive women; the transition between traditional and modern life in mountain villages in the Caucasus; and living with schizophrenia, with images taken around Coney Island. Some of the images were displayed as part of Hand and Eye: Fifteen Years of the Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize, an exhibit at the Center for Documentary Studies from Sept. 19, 2005-Jan. 8, 2006. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Berridge, Mary
Amberg, Rob
Lommasson, Jim
Eskenazi, Jason
McAdams, Dona Ann
Boxing -- Pictorial works
Coney Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works
Documentary photography
HIV-positive women -- Pictorial works
Former Soviet republics -- Pictorial works
Schizophrenia -- Social aspects
Black-and-white prints (photographs)
Chromogenic color prints
Gelatin silver prints
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
More photographs from Rob Amberg are held in the Rob Amberg Photographs collection and the Sodom Laurel Album Exhibition Photographs, both held in the Archive for Documentary Arts (Duke University).
Description of Collection
- Rob Amberg Series, 1996-2003, (4 prints)
  Four prints from I-26, Corridor of Change, by Rob Amberg and Sam Gray, an examination of the physical, economic, and social changes accompanying highway construction in the remote Appalachian mountains. Winner of the 1998 Lange-Taylor Prize. 16x20 gelatin silver prints.
  - Homemade sign mounted during exhumation of Little Iony Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, 1996. (Box 1)
  - Looking North from the visitor center overlook toward Dale and Lurethra Fluty's farm, 2003. (Box 1)
  - Power shovel churning land at Little Creek, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Supervisors inspect recent blast at Buckner's Gap, 1997. (Box 1)
- Jason Eskanazi Series, 1999, (4 prints)
  Four prints from Mountain Jews: A Lost Tribe, by Jason Eskenazi and Jennifer Gould; the transition of a centuries-old village in the Caucasus from its traditional ways of life. Winner of the 1999 Lange-Taylor Prize. 16x20 black and white prints.
  - A man gets a shave at the corner barber shop, Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999. (Box 1)
  - In the center of town, men gather at the crossroads everyday to chat, Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999. (Box 1)
  - The village maternity ward (a bird in the house is a bad omen), Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999. (Box 1)
  - Two women walk through an old Jewish cemetery on Tisha b'Av, Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999. (Box 1)
- Dona Ann McAdams Series, undated, (3 prints)
  Three prints from The Garden of Eden: Living with Schizophrenia on Coney Island, by Dona Ann McAdams and Brad Kessler; a window into the extraordinary world of people living with severe mental illness. Winner of the 2002 Lange-Taylor Prize. 16x20 gelatin silver prints.
  - Mary and the Birds. (Box 1)
  - Mary and the Birds. (Box 1)
  - Stillwell Avenue. (Box 1)
- Jim Lommasson Series, 1998-2003, (5 prints)
  Five prints from Shadow Boxers: Sweat, Sacrifice, and the Will to Survive in America's Toughest Boxing Gyms, by Jim Lommasson and Katherine Dunn, which speaks to the power of boxing to transform lives and communities. Winner of the 2004 Lange-Taylor Prize. Archival digital prints, black and white, approximately 19x15 inches.
  - Azteca Boxing Gym, East Los Angeles, 2003 (Notes: Punching bag). (Box 1)
  - Bryheim Douglas, The James Costello Boxing Gym, Philadelphia, 2003 (Notes: Man on steps). (Box 1)
  - Hand Wraps, Virg The Scourge Bohnenkamp, The Grand Avenue Boxing Gym, Portland, Oregon, 1999. (Box 1)
  - Saul Hernandez, The Grand Avenue Boxing Gym, Portland, Oregon, 1998 (Notes: Close-up face). (Box 1)
  - Wild Card Boxing Gym, Los Angeles, 2003 (Notes: Through rainy glass). (Box 1)
- Mary Berridge Series, 1996-2005, (22 prints)
  Twenty-two unmatted analog chromogenic color prints from A Positive Life: Portraits of Women Living with HIV, a collaboration between photographer Mary Berridge and writer River Houston to photograph and interview women in the North Carolina Triangle who are living with HIV/AIDS. Winner of the 1996 Lange-Taylor Prize. These prints were displayed in a 1999 exhibit at the Center for Documentary Studies. The exhibit was part of a larger, Triangle-wide program called Living with HIV/AIDS. Sixteen of the 22 prints are captioned on the back. Boxes 2, 3, and 5 house 20x24 prints, and Box 4 has prints that are 34.5 x 28.5 inches.
  - Lery Espinosa, 27, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1994, infected through sex (page 3 of publication) (Box 2)
  - Beatrice, 39, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1992, infected through sex (page 11 of publication) (Box 2)
  - April Drew, 29, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1989, infected through sex (page 28 of publication) (Box 2)
  - Laurie Priddy, 32, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1990, infected through sex (page 98 of publication) (Box 2)
  - Brenda, 35, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1994, infected through sex (page 111 of publication) (Box 2)
  - Unknown woman (Box 2)
  - Julie Evenson (Box 3)
  - Milsa "Cookie" Ramos (Box 3)
  - Meredith (Box 3)
  - Debbie Diamond (Box 3)
  - Tracie Edness-Etheredge (Box 3)
  - Alicia McWilliams (Box 3)
  - Shana Tenendah (Box 4)
  - Julie Evenson (Box 4)
  - Tracie Edness-Etheredge (Box 4)
  - Patricia Annichiarico (Box 4)
  - Woman sitting on couch smoking, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Women in green sitting outdoors in a chair, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Woman and young man standing beside a table, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Woman sitting on floor with dog and child, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Woman in white in front of magnolia [citrus?] tree, 1999, (2 copies) (Box 5)